Hello, I'm Derek Radney. Um, I'm a
pastor at Trinity Church in
Winston-Salem, North Carolina and I'm
hosting this conversation today on
behalf of the Alliance for Mission and
Renewal.
Uh, the Alliance exists to help foster a
unified, faithful, and flourishing PCA.
We just recently published our
theological vision that clarifies what
we're seeking for the PCA and I
encourage everyone today to go to
a4mr.com to learn more about that.
But, uh, part of that theological vision
that we just put out talks about our
reformed denominational identity.
And of course, worship was a huge
concern of the reformers and the
regulated principle has remained a
distinctive approach to worship by the
Presbyterian and Reformed tradition ever
since.
And when the PCA was founded in 1973 and
the BCO was adopted, the directory for
worship, aside from a few chapters on
the sacraments, was not given full
constitutional status. And so, the PCA
has never had a binding directory for
worship.
However, last year's General Assembly in
Chattanooga approved an overture to
establish a study committee to propose
revisions to the directory for worship
for authoritative use and to recommend
that the whole directory for worship
would receive full constitutional
status. So,
that committee was appointed by our
moderator Kevin DeYoung and it was just
made public a couple of weeks ago and so
today I have the honor of speaking with
a few of the members of that committee.
So, my purpose today really is to allow
that committee, uh, and these committee
members an opportunity to commend to
everyone the work that they've done and
to discuss their proposal so that
commissioners to this next General
Assembly are prepared to vote on their
recommendation. So, I'm honored today to
be joined by two committee members, uh,
teaching elder Nathan Shurden and
teaching elder Joel Saint Clair, as well
as, uh, the only advisory member of the
committee, uh, OPC teaching elder Dr.
Chad Van Dixhoorn.
So, let me just briefly introduce our
guests. Uh
Teaching Elder Nate Shurden is the
committee chairman and he's the senior
pastor of Cornerstone Presbyterian
Church in Franklin, Tennessee. He's an
adjunct professor at New College and
he's been in the PCA for 25 years,
married to his wife Christie, and he has
five children.
And then Teaching Elder Joel Saint Clair
is the senior pastor of Mosaic Community
Church in Silver Spring, Maryland.
He is the co-executive director of the
Alliance for Mission and Renewal. He's a
guest lecturer at RTS and he's been in
the PCA for 25 years as well. And he's
married with four children. And then we
have Dr. Van Dixhoorn, a professor of
church history and theology at RTS in
Charlotte, where he teaches on worship
among other things. He's authored
several books including Confessing the
Faith, A Reader's Guide to the
Westminster Confession of Faith, and
he's married to Emily and he has five
children. So, men, welcome. Thank you
for taking the time to do this. Uh I
believe this discussion will help the GA
be more prepared to do good work as we
speak as we seek the spirit's guidance
together. So, thanks for being here.
>> Thank you.
>> Yeah.
Uh so, with that I'd like to jump right
in and Nate, I'm going to start with you
and ask you as the committee chairman if
you could just talk to us about the
composition of the committee, how you
all began and conducted your work, and
just your overall impression of how you
all worked together.
>> Well, Derek, thanks once again for
having us here on the podcast. Delighted
to be with you and thanks for that
question.
Um well, I have these two dear brothers
on this committee with me alongside Gabe
Fluhrer, who is a senior minister at
First Presbyterian Church in
Chattanooga. Um Adriel Sanchez, who's
the pastor of North Park Presbyterian
Church in San Diego, California. Uh Jim
Shepherd, who was a ruling elder out of
Perimeter Church in Atlanta. Uh John
Wingard, who was a professor of
humanities at Covenant College. And
Nathan Partain, who was a ruling elder
and worship director at Redeemer
Presbyterian Church in Indianapolis. And
so, these uh seven members of the
committee alongside our advisory
committee member Chad joined us. And it
was from the beginning, Derek, a delight
to be with these brothers. Um grateful
for Kevin DeYoung's choice in bringing
us together.
Um and despite his his choice of
inviting me to be on the committee,
which was his momentary lapse of
judgment, everybody else on the
committee was an incredible asset and a
blessing that really represented the
spectrum of the PCA in many ways. Men
from different backgrounds, men from
different parts of the country,
men from different influences, who love
the Bible, love the reformed faith, and
are committed to worship and worship of
the living God. And And to be able to be
with these brothers from the very
beginning as we started out was to begin
our time in prayer. We actually wrote a
little prayer guide for us from the very
beginning to just say, "Brothers, let's
start praying for this work. We've got a
daunting challenge ahead of us, and
there are a million ways to get this
wrong,
but with the Lord's help and by his
spirit leading us,
there's so much profitable and good work
that I think we can do for the good of
the PCA." And I think from the very
beginning the Lord began answering those
prayers. We got together on a Zoom call,
introduced each other,
heard from one another just learning
each other's stories and testimonies,
prayed together for the work, and began
to study. We read directories, we went
back into history starting all the way
back in the 16th century of the
Reformation and coming all the way
forward, and uh to do the work of just
exploring what a directory is, how it's
functioned historically, what that would
mean for the PCA at this given time, and
um and and the Lord met us as we
continued to meet in Zoom meetings and
then finally in person in Charlotte,
North Carolina with some great
hospitality by the Van Dixhorns while we
were there. Um the Lord continued to
just bring a spirit of unity in our time
together um even in our differences and
deliberations and in our our our
sparring back and forth together as
brothers, there was a incredible amount
of charity and incredible amount of
unity that we that we shared together.
And much to our surprise coming with a
unanimous uh recommendation of these
directory revisions. And I think one of
our own sadnesses is just not to even be
able to spend as much time together that
these days. I have seven new friends uh
in the PCA, some of which I knew
marginally, but just the spirit of this
occasion and this opportunity to serve
together has been truly a blessing.
>> That's great.
Well, Chad, you're the the lone non-PCA
uh member uh and you're a busy guy. So,
I guess uh one question I wanted to ask
you is just what motivated you to accept
this invitation to be an advisory member
and take on all this work, and then was
it really worth your time at the end of
the day?
>> Well, Derek, I love being called an
advisory member. I'm probably an advisor
to the members rather than an advisory
member, a very very important
distinction uh that's been so helpfully
articulated uh in another context. Uh
so,
I'm a fraternal delegate to the PCA, and
I love everybody in the PCA equally. Uh
so so, when I get a chance to work with
a bunch of brothers,
uh that's that's great. I I had
suggested that
I I just kind of look at the finished
product and and see if there's any uh
questions I might have to answer and and
and the the brothers wanted more
fellowship than that. So, that that was
that was wonderful. I have been studying
the history of worship for a while
early church, medieval church,
reformation especially the Westminster
Assembly.
And and I teach on worship. So, I
thought I might have something to add.
So, you know, given given an opportunity
for some for some good fellowship and
reflection given a chance to think aloud
with other brothers and learn from them.
I thought that was a good move and I it
definitely was. I've been very edified
by this whole process, grateful for it.
>> Well, great. Thank you. We're thankful
for your willingness to help us out and
to to contribute to it. So, all right.
Well, I'd love to just throw this out to
all of you and just you know, allow you
to take a moment to just make your case
for what you've put together.
You know, you've you're not just putting
forward the directory for worship, but
you're also making a particular
procedural motion that this is voted on
as a whole and not with you know,
without amendments. And so, could you
talk about both the work as a whole and
also why people should you know, vote
for that procedural motion?
>> On the procedural motion just to to
speak to that first. I think it's
helpful to understand when there has
been
the directory of public worship
available in our current BCO but not
constitutional and then a a group is put
together by the moderator that broadly
reflects our current denomination with
excellent expertise from our lone
advisory member. Then when you put those
things together and we put all this work
together, it we're looking at all of
this history and then trying to write
chapters of BCO revisions, right? And
so, the the best way that I can put this
is if If were just changing a few lines
in one of the sacrament chapters that
was a constitutional, we would invite
amendments and debate. But when you've
read
all of this background and then crafted
something as a group, as a committee
that's broadly representative, then to
put such a large change before the
assembly
makes sense, I think, to
vote it all either up or down or refer
back to the committee if you see fit.
But our hope would be to to approve all
of these changes recognizing that if
there's one particular piece that you
wanted to amend, there's always going to
be opportunity for that down the road.
That's that future amendments are not
barred. What we're asking is to cover
such a big ground
or such a significant chunk of BZO
revisions that we do that
with the committee's work.
>> It's good.
What about just the work as a whole? I
mean, what would be the basic pitch
you'd give for what you guys have put
together?
>> Derek, one of the things that as we
sought to craft the revisions that are
before you is to give something that
would be taking our historic and
reformed and confessional faith that we
love and the practices and principles of
historic reformed worship in an
up-to-date pastorally useful
and
document that would be able to get be
formative for the lives of congregations
and instructive to sessions and pastors
as they seek to craft services and
inculcate a spirit of worship within the
congregation.
Our prior directory without the
constitutional status status that it has
has so much to commend and stands in the
long line of faithful directories that
extend all the way back to the time of
the Westminster Confession of Faith.
And yet, as we read it, there was
language vocabulary that didn't ring or
resonate in the same way as it would
have in our own current context and
climate. And there were some things that
were stated
didactically and maybe even
in a in a more much more direct and
short manner that we actually thought
could be unpacked with some greater
depth and even an elevated level of
prose to help and encourage and inspire
the the lofty vision of worship that we
hope captures the heart of the PCA. And
one of the things that's been
encouraging about some of the feedback
that we've received is that folks who
have read through the directory seeing
the echoes of the previous directory and
its history playing in to this revision,
it's also devotional in its spirit and
in its manner so much so that as one
brother put it to me in a text message
yesterday, I read the opening chapter
and I can't wait for Sunday. And I
thought, oh, that's something of what we
hoped this directory might strike. And
and so as we put it together as a whole,
that's part of the reason we thought it
was a bolt of cloth is taking out a
little section or or taking another
section here doing chapter by chapter
might not have the same impact of taking
it all at once in the way that we're
bringing it before the assembly. And so
I think that commends this directory and
and the early returns and responses to
that have been
obviously there's always mixed comments
as things get get out there, but but
very encouraged by the expression that
this document not only guided and
directed and gave general principles and
practices for worship, it made me want
and desire to worship my living God. And
that's a big part of why we why we're
commending this revision to you.
>> Yeah.
Yeah.
Um well, I was going to I was going to
ask about that, particularly the the
kind of function of the directory for
worship uh in giving general principles,
you know, prescribing the kind of
essential elements, but then there's
just a lot of um advice or guidance or
kind of pointing in a direction. And
I've heard some people just say, "Well,
what's the point of that? Why do we need
to make that constitutional?" What What
would be your response to that sort of
um question about about a directory?
>> Yeah, maybe you start with just a
practical note on on this uh Derek.
There's a
that you know, when you've you've
existed as a denomination for for coming
up on 54 years and you've not had a
constitutional directory. And there is a
broad spectrum of of worship practice in
in the PCA. And um
recognizing that to establish any kind
of boundary or any kind of margin is is
going to be a something of an uphill
battle. Um
um it's not a perfect parallel, but I
think of uh trying to instill a curfew
in with my 18-year-old son, but you
know, two or three years after he's been
out riding around everywhere and then
decide, you know, I think we're going to
rein this in. It's a little harder to
establish anything like that. And so,
there was a sense of uphill struggle
even from the very beginning that this
would be a challenge. Um I joked in
another conversation that I would get um
a comment to for folks when they saw I
was a part of this committee to say,
"Hey, congratulations and condolences on
on this work." because I think they saw
the heavy lifting that uh and the big
challenge that was before us.
So, as we thought through the directory,
there are many things that there's a lot
that could be said more in every chapter
and there's more either stricture or
more direction that could be given.
Um and yet there's a wisdom to working
through general principle biblical and
confessional standards to work towards
winning the heart of the denomination to
a vision for worship over time that
would make more sense on things that
probably could be said even a little bit
tighter here or there or this could be
adjusted a little bit here or there
to say we would we would love for this
to have a formative impact in the life
of the denomination over time and not
try to address every single matter and
everybody's particular matter in in this
directory. And I think sometimes we you
know I'm I'm guilty of the us too to say
I want a quick fix or a one a piece of
legislation that's going to give me
everything I want. When in fact we
underestimate what would happen in 5 10
15 years of men being trained in the
directory taking vows to uphold it
instructing congregations in it
that long heart mind work that would
have a formative discipleship in the
congregation
in the denomination would be I think our
heart with this directory is that it
gets us on the road. It's not the
complete destination to probably
anywhere we would go. As you know we
like to change some things in our
constitution over time in the PCA. We
would anticipate that to be the case
here. But we believe that we're well on
the way to getting in the direction we
believe the denomination really is
charged us to chart with this ad interim
committee.
>> Yeah.
>> And can I just add positively not not
only what Nate has highlighted for the
current uh PCA in terms of its ministers
and churches, but I think for people
coming into the reformed faith, uh not
to assume that they understand what are
the elements of worship and what does
that look like? And and so, if you take
a directory of public worship, it's
instructive not only for people who are
already in, but for
at our church in Mosaic Silver Spring,
people are showing up and and they're
showing up because we're a neighborhood
congregation
who's worshiping the Lord, not
necessarily because they Googled uh PCA
or reformed church locally. And so, as
they come in, this directory functions
now as uh something for us to be able to
use to help show this is how the Bible
can be understood in terms of shaping
the elements of worship pulling from our
rich tradition. And I hope in that way
it it would be a help, right? In in
discipling people who are coming in. And
and then the constitutionality side of
that is just to give it the seriousness
with which historically reformed
churches have given uh public worship as
well as their doctrine, right? And And
so, that's how positively put, to add to
what Nate said, I I could see this
coming together.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> So,
Joel's point reminds me of a of a of a
nerd fact, and that is when the
Westminster Assembly produced its
directory for worship,
um
a rule was passed that churches needed
to buy a copy.
Uh and it's it just strikes me now for
the first time. It's interesting that
it's not that ministers needed to buy a
copy, churches did.
Um uh be- because the minister of the
church was expected to use it, but but
others were too. I mean, there are there
are things in the directory that are
really meant for everybody.
Um
and and to have something we could
actually give to everybody. I mean, I I
don't expect that uh the PCA is going to
sort of print this in pamphlet form,
uh
but uh but but nonetheless, to be able
to give something like that to someone,
should the PCA actually like this and
adopt it eventually
with you know could be encouraging.
>> Yeah.
So, I hear you guys talking about the
sort of
guidance and even training function that
this can have. Uh but Joel I'm going to
ask you this cuz there are people in the
denomination who are concerned with
something like this that it's just going
to lead to many many battles in the
coming years.
Uh to write in rules that you guys
didn't put in this first step. And um
you know
we all agree there's reform worship and
that should point us in certain
directions, but the farther down that
road you get the more there's often
debates about little applications of
those principles form circumstance so
on. So, what what would you say Joel in
particular to those in our denomination
who are concerned about this opening a
door for just a bunch of fighting?
>> Yeah, I
I understand the concern to fight about
things or or really I think the concern
isn't so much that people don't care
about the truth. I think the concern is
rooted in we all only have so much time
and energy and how is a denomination do
we want to focus that time and energy?
And if that's the underlying concern of
that kind of question, I would just
encourage the asker of the question the
questioner and and say hey throughout
this process the committee itself
represented
a pretty broad stretch of the PCA. And
then through our review process, the
people we asked to read this document,
it was a broad swath of the PCA. And and
now we expect that what was what's been
produced positively
would give us
renewed focus on what draws the PCA
together on the things that we can agree
upon and and draw encouragement from
that to positively state hey this is
worship. Let's focus on this.
Now, if someone in that context, if
someone wants to say, "Well,
but this may generate more fights." I
guess in the words of Aragorn and in the
Two Towers,
you know, passing if the concern is that
we risk BCO battles by passing the deep
you know, the Directory of Public
Worship, I would just say that BCO
battles are already upon us and passing
the Directory of Public Worship and
making it constitutional, I would hope
is a helpful guide to say, "Hey, here's
where a broad stretch of the PCA in
representative ways says, this is how we
understand this to work. Trust our
sessions and and here's a guide for the
elements for faithful worship. And to
that extent, I would hope it would be an
encouragement to that questioner in the
same way that it's been an encouragement
to me through this process. That may
have been one of my concerns coming in.
Well, what's the product's going to be?
And and yet, Derek, by not only going
through the process of working on this,
but then just reading it and saying,
"Well, how does this line up with how I
currently understand worship and what my
congregation is doing?" I would say that
the
the vast majority of the PCA can see
themselves in this directory and be
encouraged. And that would be my hope.
>> So
So, here's a ramble and it could be a
little naive. Um
So, I'm listening to Joel and
appreciating what he's saying.
It seems to me that this directory as
presented
um
reflects
kind of a variety of positions
in the PCA and at the same time, it it
does commend a vision for reformed
worship that some congregations or
elderships might find more challenging
than others.
Um we we think that's that's helpful to
be to be challenged.
Um
but let's say that
um ministers in the PCA
uh consistently began to offer
prayers uh in a worship service that
were just so powerful.
Um and so deeply moving that
congregations everywhere began to want
their minister to pray a lot more.
Or people who are preparing for ministry
to pray a lot more.
That That would be a a sort of a
different PCA and a different PCA
That's not to say it's not happening in
the PCA. This is why this is a bit of a
ramble and kind of scary. But, it you
know, if if that were happening in
orders of magnitude more than it does
now, and everyone began to want more of
that,
well, then maybe a revision to the
directory for public worship would come
someday, and the people in that PCA
would find that plausible and want that.
But, this is a directory for sort of the
PCA that is.
And as a denomination changes, that's
when it will find proposed changes
plausible.
Um and so
again, I promised to ramble. I think I
delivered.
>> Well, I think you're touching on I think
part of what I'm I'm I'm identifying in
the PCA is there is kind of in the PCA a
more evangelical leaning dimension that
that emphasizes lay participation in um
in praying publicly and reading
scripture
uh and even leading music and all that.
And then there's a more historically
reformed part of the PCA that sees
ministers or elders or officers uh
having the dominant role in the kind of
public dimensions of worship. And those
parts of the PCA
um
are reflected in what you guys have put
together, but you're also kind of
pointing in a direction. And the
question is is is that direction you're
pointing going to leave some people
behind or
is it going to bring change over time
where the more evangelical leaning side
shifts to the more historically reformed
side. So, I think that's the tension
that I'm feeling in this. I'm personally
very comfortable with what you guys have
put together,
but I also know that a lot of folks and
and maybe you can speak to this have
already expressed this didn't go far
enough, you know, we didn't really do
reformed worship here and I'm voting
against it because this is actually
giving approval of those
those, you know, evangelical type
PCAers. So, I don't know how you'd
respond to that Nate or Chad about the
it's not restrictive enough objection.
>> It's it's more reformed inspiration than
reformed legislation.
>> That that's a good way of putting it.
>> At this point.
>> Yeah, I think that's a good word.
>> That's a good word, Chad. And and
there's a couple of things with that.
Derek, it's a great question and I think
to just emphasize too that this
eight-member committee, seven voting
members,
I think would to a person say we none of
us got everything we wanted in this
directory per se. I know Joel and I went
back and forth on language in
potentially a chapter where there is
some disagreement in the PCA. And and
and Joel suggested some language that we
hang hung with for a while. We came back
and we changed that language and I
labored for something that I wanted to
see didn't happen on on the committee.
And yet what came together in in in as
we were and that could be reduplicated
in a few other places for sure
throughout the work of the directory
is what we hope to establish would be
the normative principles that we see in
historic and confessional reformed
worship and biblically speaking, you
know, the reading of scripture publicly
is one of the the hotly debated
subjects. And we see that that strong
principle that is given to us in 1
Timothy 4:13 about the the minister
being given to the reading and the and
the preaching of of the word. And we
wanted to see that as the normative
principle, and you see that throughout
the directories looking back
historically. And even since the
adoption act and and the directories in
the American scene often still allowed
for there to be a measure of of
elasticity, shall we say, um with
regards to that practice. You had the
language of the normative principle of
the teaching elder being the um the
public reader prayer um in the worship
service, or you had the language or any
authorized person.
Or any authorized person. And that
language often appealed to interns or or
licentious and others who are training
in in the ministry. But notice that the
language was entrusted to the session.
It was entrusted to the session to to
make that determination. And so as we
crafted language in that chapter and
also in the public reading chapter and
in the prayer chapter,
we recognized that, "Hey, the normative
principle is here. A teaching elder, a
ruling elder historically in the
Reformed Presbyterian faith, is the
reader and the and the prayer of God's
word in the midst of a service."
And um and yet if that is not the case
in a particular instance,
the session needs to have a good reason.
They need to have seriously considered,
they need to have been deliberate in
their action to the suitability of who
it is that they chose. Um and we're
entrusting our court uh locally in a
denomination that is uh ordered even in
that grassroots uh way, uh we're
entrusting the court to make that
decision. And yet saying,
"Hey, take seriously the Bible's
teaching and the Reformed precedent.
Um the Bible's teaching and the reformed
precedent says the minister should have
a prominent role in these realities. And
so So, there is a normative principle,
there's pastoral direction, and yet
there isn't exclusivity that is is is
put forward. And And the reality, Derek,
in that is, you know, so we're wrestling
with that. We think we're navigating a
path. We're also asking the realistic
question.
Um we've got to bring this to General
Assembly. It has to go to 2/3 of the
presbyteries. It has to come back to
General Assembly the next year.
And And Derek, I think the reality is we
you have a a path that these revisions
have to take in in a denomination
that um has appropriate checks and
balances, where it has to pass the
General Assembly, has to make its way
through 2/3 of the presbyteries, and
then come back to General Assembly and
be passed again. And um and we've all
watched BCO amendments and um and and
and uh different legislation make its
journey and die the death in the
presbyteries and and never get to that
point. And I think all of us on the
committee just said, "Having a directory
that is constitutional
uh in the life of the PCA, even if there
are principled compromises, which we say
at the front of our report that we make
throughout, it is worth it for the
long-term good and health of the PCA to
get to this part and and to see the
long-term uh effect that that's going to
have denominationally. So So, looking at
the principle and the practical let us
to not try to adjudicate every matter
from this one piece of legislation."
>> Well, one of the things you guys wrote
in your introduction uh was the that
this was a historically sensitive
rewrite. And you gave a number of
reasons for that. You said you wanted to
present it uh reformed worship in a more
positive manner.
Um you wanted to put in more biblical
and confessional language, but you also
noted that um
that our context deserved
a sort of different writing. Um and I'm
curious what that context is that you're
talking about there. Is that kind of
historical,
uh is it cultural, is it PCA context, is
it all of those things? I'm I'm curious.
Maybe Chad, you have some thoughts on
this. What context you were thinking
about there or contexts?
>> Well, uh
you know, broadly speaking, uh we are a
couple hundred years after the 1788
uh directory, which the you know, the
PCA's non-binding directory draws on
fairly heavily. There's these other
developments through history. Um
but we needed to deal with things like
uh
like what do we do about online worship?
How do we How do we encourage, try to
inspire people to see the the importance
of worshipping, you know, in in person?
Um
I you you know, it's good to
speak about Psalms and hymns, but
there's other varieties of songs. Can we
Can we address that, too?
Um
so So, we're dealing with a a changed
time.
Uh or I also wanted to I The committee
thought it was important as well, too,
uh
to remember that there has been
diversity pre-PCA.
Um
And uh you know, I I happened to have
spent last summer working spending the
whole summer looking at the Westminster
Assembly's debates over over worship. Um
And there were people who thought that
the minister only uh should read the
word, and there were those who thought
he should read it if no one else was
available.
Um and then lots of other positions in
between uh about which, you know,
everyone had to speak to at least once,
uh just like as in PCA and OPC General
Assemblies. Um
So, So, there there's been variety for a
while and um
uh recognition of that important and
then just trying to state long held
dearly bought privileges
in in a way that's fresh and
communicates to this generation just an
updated wording
sometimes pointing out that something's
a privilege
where where perhaps I had not been
highlighted previously all all those
things struck us
>> really important.
>> Yeah.
Just for for example I'm just thinking
about a wording recommendation that Joel
made at one point.
You know we're we're wondering about
Joel you have to remind me if I if I if
I flag here. I think we're talking about
about you know new members coming into
the church
we're speaking about faith and I'm
probably butchering this but I I think
we're saying do we need to say faith in
Christ quite as often. And
Joel and a couple others in context
where a lot of people are people of
faith
in their churches
coming to hear the gospel but not
actually believers.
Joel said actually it's really important
to be emphasizing that we're looking for
faith in Christ here not just faith
and and so we we actually went through
and made made sure that each time we
spoke about faith that we were
clarifying that we're talking about a
believing
in Christ in particular and not just
faith in general and so on something
which in 1788 or 1894 would not have
been
would not have had to be in
>> You need clarity. Yeah.
>> All right. I've got a couple questions
that they're kind of minor in some ways
but I feel like you guys have done a
great job of talking big picture. I'm
curious about a few things I wanted to
ask you about. For instance, why are
there chapters on marriage and
visitation of the sick and funerals and
days of Thanksgiving, and fasting, and
and Christian worship in the home, if
this is a directory for public worship.
Maybe Joel, you can tackle that.
>> Yeah, I'm happy happy to give give this
a go. So So this has been the case with
directories since the Reformation. Um
and there are a number of worship public
worship adjacent topics,
which have always been addressed in this
context. So private worship is not
public worship, but when speaking about
public worship, it just seems so
important to to address what we might do
in the home. Um you know, visiting the
sick has long been included because it's
such a good Sabbath activity.
Um and because sometimes we are
worshiping with the sick person.
Um
so
you know
marriage marriage offers a wonderful
context for for the gathering of the
saints, and a worship in the context of
marriage.
It you know, graveside services, again,
there's prayer, there's reading. And so
so so these things are all sort of
public worship adjacent, or kind of
irregular, or unusual forms of
uh of of public worship. And so they've
always been in directories, often been
in the very order that they're here.
There's a few more topics, actually,
that say the 1788 directory has
that we don't have. This is more
reflective of the 1645 directory of the
assembly than the Philadelphia assembly,
if you will, of 1788. Um so that's a
quick answer.
>> Yeah, that's good. That's good. All
right, what why don't you tell us also
why is minister used in the directory
for public worship rather than teaching
elder?
>> So So the committee talked about this.
The the Book of Church Order, of course,
I as a OPC minister I actually teach PCA
polity, which is a a thing,
which I can which which I I can justify
in complete sentences, but
the BCO constantly talks about teaching
elders, which is helpful in the context
of governance when you're distinguishing
between types of elders and their
responsibilities.
But when you turn to the subject of
worship, ministers
the committee recognized that there's
been a historic use of the term minister
and and and for good reason. Teaching
elder highlights really just uh one
function of a minister.
And the apostles say that they need to
give themselves to a ministry of of word
and prayer.
Um and
you know, ministry, if if you will,
allows for a broader lens. Ministry also
suggests um
a relationship. You know, we are
servants of someone.
And I think it also suggests a manner.
So so so there's a there's a relation,
there's a manner, there's a broader
focus, all of which is appropriate
um
uh especially for a director for
worship, which is why it's
usually been the term that's used. So
we're just picking up on that historic
and thoughtful use.
>> Okay, well, maybe let's just end with
this last one uh unless there's other
thoughts you want to add, but if this
passes, you know, what what it would be
the best outcome for you guys in terms
of how this would impact the PCA? I know
you've already alluded to that in many
ways, but what would you love to see
happen? And it doesn't just have to be
related to worship, it could be any
number of things, but what would be the
impact of us passing this?
Best case scenario.
>> I you know, one of the thing one of my
hopes Derek with this is I mean, if you
think about worship as the high calling
that the Lord has given to his church
and the eternal calling that we have as
as followers of the Lord Jesus Christ.
Um I am just wild enough to dream that
the Lord might use something like this
to further
advance the peace and the purity of the
PCA in the holiness of worship and in
its beauty and in its wonder.
And that he would he would cause us as
as pastors, as teaching elders, ruling
elders, he calls us to rally around one
another in the unity that we will one
day fully and completely share around
his throne of grace.
There will be no worship wars one day
when we all gather around that throne of
grace in the second in the second the
second coming of the Lord Jesus Christ.
And it seems to me that a denomination
when it sets its sights eternally on the
call of worship and labors with a
directory like this in that manner, it
has greater potential about what it
doesn't have or what it didn't do, but
what the Lord might be pleased to do as
he shapes us by it in the days to come
by his spirit. And I would love to see
that happen.
I'll just say and I think Joel give
testimony to this and and Chad as well,
he did that in our in our committee.
I
you know, I grew being with these
brothers and and realized that hey,
we're not on the same page on
everything. But we could principally
disagree and and labor together and and
come to the conclusions that this is a
directory that will be for the good of
the PCA in the days to come. And I think
I told the man I joked at the end I said
brothers we may be the only people
benefited by this directory in the end.
This may be this may be the end all and
be all of what the Lord has in store for
this directory is our blessing. And I
said praise be to his name if that's the
case. But can you imagine should the
Lord
be pleased to unite us in the way that
he already has united us in Christ and
for that future worship that we will
enjoy forever.
I am
idealist enough to pray and labor
towards that end. So that would be
something of what I hope in the days to
come that it would be if as we we just
we will argue over this, Derek. We will
we will um
it's you know, it's we will argue over
it because we care, because it matters,
because it's important. Um it's
different with arguing over it than
quarreling over it. That's different.
>> Yeah.
>> And what I would hope that we would
learn to do is argue well and and lean
into the scripture, lean into the
confession, lean into the love of one
another and not quarrel, but labor for
the peace and the purity of the church
until Jesus returns. So,
um I'm going to get preaching if you're
not careful there, Derek.
>> Yeah, yeah. That's great. I appreciate
that, Nate. Do you guys have have
anything to add to that?
>> Yeah, I I would say that
my hope is that if this were passed that
it it becomes
um both an encouragement and a
challenge. Uh that it would become an
encouragement to people who are not as
familiar
uh with reformed worship to say, "Let me
consider these elements." And that from
start to finish they could read this and
and then go back to the scripture
references and try to say, "Oh, this is
this is how worship unfolds in the life
of the church." And in that way it would
be a source of great encouragement to
show up with a new vigor on the Lord's
Day. Uh my hope is that it would be a
challenge not to the individual. Uh I
hope this doesn't challenge an
individual to say, "Wait, this doesn't
prescribe constitutionally exactly what
I want for every other PCA church." My
hope is that the challenge would rather
be one for sessions
to think through, "How do I take these
elements of worship and in my local
context put these elements on display to
encourage the hearts of our people as
well as the hearts of our neighborhood
and our community for people who are
coming in." So, it was interesting to me
to notice that in past directories
there's always this challenge for
preachers to not preach so so but to
leave room for singing. It it feels like
singing is constantly being held out as
a way to like, "Hey, and don't forget to
sing, right? And and maybe you can't you
could sing more." And and
that may be playing a little fast and
loose with the language. Chad can can
correct you after I've or correct me
after I've finished, but it those are
the types of challenges that I would
hope this directory functions as where
someone could say, "Huh, let me think
about how we're using music in the life
of our worship on a Sunday morning. Let
me think about how we are using prayers
or scripture reading, not just before
the sermon, but for other elements. Let
me Let me think about how frequently or
regularly the Lord's Supper is a part of
our church, and that sessions in their
various contexts are thinking through
that." That would be incredible for what
we could accomplish with and and
positively thinking with the Directory
of Worship, as opposed to just is this
saying everything that I want it to say,
thinking how can we encourage and
promote a view of reformed worship
across the denomination in all of the
various towns
and rural locations and cities that the
PCA finds itself in Canada and in the
US.
>> From outside the PCA, that sounds
delightful.
And I join them in praying
for for that. I
I'm so blessed to be worshipping in PCA
churches very often. And uh
and I'm I'm I'm thankful to hear this
this vision. And thank you for having
us, Derek.
>> Yeah, thank you all for your time. And I
just will say for myself, I I share
those hopes for the PCA, and that's my
prayer as well.
I think, like you said, Nate, we're
going to argue, but let's argue well,
and I think you all have already
demonstrated the the sort of love and
charity and humility and sharpening that
hopefully we we all learn to do better
as a denomination. And we do grow in
unity of mind
as we are continuing to learn how to be
faithful to the word of God and to
worship God. So,
thank you guys for all your work. Uh
thank you for uh the time explaining it
to us here today. And uh thank you
everyone who's been listening and
watching. Uh we hope to um have good
conversations and talk about our
denomination and pray that the Lord
would uh bless the work of our hands.
So, thanks everyone.
>> Thank you.